PROFESSOR: OK, so let's talk
about why A* works.
I claimed A* was optimal, and
let's see why that is.
Well, let's make some assumptions.
So, here's a diagram that reflects
some point in the
execution of a search.
So here's a search tree, the
start state's at top.
We hear some note n, and this thing is
going to have some cumulative path
class G of have n, and then an estimate
of this forward cost here to
the goal is going to be H of n.
OK, so you can think about those.
And on this, we're going to imagine
that B here is a bad goal.
So this is a goal.
It passes the goal test,
but it's suboptimal.
G is an optimal goal node.
So it's a goal node with least cost.
And the claim is that if G is an
optimal goal node, and B is a
suboptimal goal node, and H is
admissible, then under A* tree search,
G will be removed from
the fringe before B.
That's the claim.
That's enough to give optimality.
If we know that the optimal goals will
be removed before the bad suboptimal
goals, we're done.
That's optimality.
So let's prove that G is going to come
off the fringe before B. Proof's
actually pretty easy, and
it's got one key idea.
We imagine we're at some point
that B is on the fringe.
If B's not on the fringe,
we don't have to worry.
There's no chance of it coming
off the fringe if it
hasn't gone on the fringe.
So we imagine we have some point
where b is on the fringe.
And so this dotted line here represents
the things that are on the
fringe, and it cuts through
the tree in some way.
So B is on the French, and were afraid
it might pop off before G does.
So G may not be on the fringe, right?
But some ancestor n of G is.
How do I know?
Well, at the start of the algorithm,
the root was on the fringe.
That's an ancestor of G. When the root
comes off, its children go on.
And if you think about this path from
the root down to G, at the beginning,
the first node, the start
state, is on.
After I pop that start node, one of its
children, whatever its descendant
is on this path, is on.
When I pop that, the next one down on
the path will be on, and at all times,
we're making a certain amount of
progress along this optimal path to G.
So we know that maybe G's on the fringe,
but even if it's not, some
ancestor G of N is on the fringe.
Right, so now we've got a race.
We've got B on the fringe, and we're
afraid B is going to pop off, and
we've got n, which may be G or it
may be an ancestor of G. Right.
The claim is, n will be expanded
before B is expanded.
And if that's true, then we're fine
because n will be expanded, and then
its child will be another such n, and it
will be expanded, and eventually G
will be expanded before B.
So I need to argue to you that, if we're
in this configuration where B is
on the fringe and n is on the fringe,
that n is going to come
off first in A*.
Well, that's actually pretty easy
because the priority of n is less than
or equal to the priority of G. So if you
consider n to G, n's f cost, which
includes true costs up here and lower
bound costs H to get to G is less than
actually
getting to G. Why?
That's because of admissibility.
So n will off before G. And we
also that G has a better
priority f than B. Why?
That's what suboptimality of B means,
because H is zero at the goal.
What this means is that all ancestors of
G are going to be expanded before B
ever comes off the fringe.
And so what you'll see is, even if B
gets on the fringe, it's going to sit
there blocking until every node along
the path to G takes its turn.
So even though B may end up on the
fringe easily, G will come off first,
and that means we have optimality.
It also echoes what we saw before, that
the important thing is not when
you find a goal and put it on
the fringe, but when you
remove from the fringe.
That's when you know it's
safe to declare.